Guide to the Ray Watkin Strange Research Materials for "William Ward Watkin and the Rice Institute,"1917-1985 MS 465
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Ray Watkin Strange Research Materials for "William Ward Watkin and the Rice Institute"
1917-1985
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Strange, Ray Watkin Hoagland
MS 465
5.5 Linear Feet 11 boxes
This material covers the architectural career of the Ms. Strange's father, William Ward Watkin, including his private architecture practice and well as his relationship with Rice Institute as Supervising Architect, touching briefly on his personal life. The material was gathered by Ms. Strange and much of it served as research for the book: William Ward Watkin and The Rice Institute by Patrick James Nicholson (published 1991 by Gulf Pub. Co.).
Biographical / Historical
Annie Ray Watkin, eldest of three children of William Ward Watkin and Annie Ray Townsend, was born May 11, 1915 in Houston, TX at the Watkin residence, 5009 Caroline. She was home schooled through second grade by her mother and then entered the Kinkaid School (San Jacinto @ Elgin) where she graduated from the tenth grade. The family traveled to France in 1928-29 for her father to study architecture. In 1930 she entered Chatham Hall, an Episcopal Preparatory School in Chatham, VA and majored in American history. She attended Rice Institute from Sept. 1932 to June 1936, graduating with a baccalaureate degree in liberal arts with a major in French. She was queen of Rice Institute's Archi-Arts Ball in 1936 and the same year was inducted into Phi Beta Kappa.
Ray married Carl Biehl, a shipping executive, in Dec. 1939 and moved with him to Washington, DC where he had accepted a position with the War Shipping Department. After her husband left for England with the Army Transportation Corps, Ray returned to Houston and pursued a master of arts degree in the history of art at Rice Institute under the auspices of the School of Architecture and professor James Chillman. She received her MA in 1944. Ray served as secretary of the Houston chapter of the American Red Cross through 1945 and as Red Cross Arts and Skills Corps Chairman in 1947. Ray formed the Rice Alumni History Committee in 1975, now the Alumni Archives Committee, and permanently endows the William Ward Watkin Traveling Scholarship in Architecture. Ray divorced Biehl in 1955 and in 1961 married Henry W. Hoagland, spending time between Boston, Houston, Kennebunkport, ME and Tucson, AZ. Following Hoagland's death, Ray married Robert F. Strange on Jan. 25, 1997 and now lives in Brenham, TX.
Scope and Contents
These materials document the career of William Ward Watkin, including his private architecture practice and well as his relation with Rice Institute, and touches briefly on his personal life. The material was maintained by Watkin's daughter, Ray Watkin Strange, and served as research for the book: William Ward Watkin and The Rice Institute by Patrick James Nicholson (published 1991 by Gulf Pub. Co.). Dates range from 1917-1985, and formats include correspondence, notes, clippings, interviews, brochures, sketches, typescripts, photographs.
Access Restrictions
No access restrictions; this material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center. Boxes 1-11 store inside vault.
Acquisition Information
The materials were donated by Ray Watkin Strange and Mr. & Mrs. (Rosemary Watkin) Nolan E. Barrick in 1965 and 1979, and deeded as a gift in 1998. Addenda in 1999, 2000.
Related Material
William Ward Watkin Papers MS352
William Ward Watkin and Ray Watkin Hoagland [Strange] information/vertical files
Index Terms
Subjects
Architecture; Architects -- Texas; Universities and colleges
Document Types
clippings (information artifacts); interviews; corrrespondence; sketchbooks; photographs; typescripts; notes; brochures
Places
Houston (Texas) -- Buildings, structures, etc.
Subjects (Persons)
Strange, Ray Watkin Hoagland; Watkin, William Ward; Nicholson, Patrick James
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University; Rice Architectural Society; Rice University. Department of Architecture
- Series I: William Ward Watkin's Architectural Career, 1923-52; 5 linear inches (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes newsclips, correspondence and published materials regarding William Ward Watkin's architectural projects.
  - Architectural works, general-newsclips, etc. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Published materials on Watkin's architectural works: (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Museum of Fine Arts, Houston, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Houston: An Architectural Guide, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Touch of Time; Myth, Memory, and the Self, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Church Building in Boston, 1720-1970, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Flying Owls; Rice Institute from the Air, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [oversize materials removed to Box 5] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brochure of the Work of Wm Ward Watkin, Architect, c. 1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Fondren Library, The Rice Institute, Houston, TX prospectus, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pen and ink rendering on paper by H.C. Jemison of sanctuary screen at Christ Episcopal Church, Houston [designed by W.W. Watkin], 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Art Work of Houston, Texas; published in Twelve Parts; the Gravure Illustration Co., Parts 1-4, 6-12, 1904: (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Julia Ideson Building, Houston Public Library-Reopening and restoration, (designed by R.A. Cram; W.W. Watkin, Supervising Architect), Feb. 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Article materials on R.A. Cram, 1898, 1925, 1970s, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cram, Goodhue and Ferguson: Plans and Architectural Drawings for the Development of the Rice Institute Campus, 1909-1930; designs by W.W. Watkin in Boston office (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dr. Mrs. George Hill House, Houston, TX, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Texas Technological College, Lubbock, TX, Administration Building, 1923-28, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: William Ward Watkin at Rice Institute/University, 1917-52 [1960s-70s]; 12.5 linear inches (Box 1-4)
  This series includes records of William Ward Watkin's involvement with academics, specifically the Architecture Department, and athletics, campus buildings and Rice history.
  - Rice Architectural Society: Constitution and minutes:, 1917-23, 1926-28 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rice Architectural Society: Minutes, 1934-42 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rice Architectural Society: Minutes, 1942-47 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rice Architectural Society: General, 1963-68 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Rice Architectural Society: Archi-Arts Balls, 1950s-70s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Rice Architecture graduates list, advanced degrees to, 1916-59; 1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Rice Institute School of Architecture MCMXXVIII, [1928] (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Rice School of Architecture: Annual Reports, 1957, 1961, 1969-70, 1970-71 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Rice School of Architecture: William Ward Watkin Traveling Fellowship, 1960s, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Rice School of Architecture: Rice ASC/AIA constitution, by-laws, 1958, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Rice School of Architecture: Weekly reports, 1967-69, 72 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Rice Architecture Department Faculty: James Chillman, Jr., 1916-1970s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Rice Architecture Department Faculty: Francis X. Keally, 1929-70s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Rice Architecture Department Faculty: William McVey, 1960s-70s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Rice Architecture Department Faculty: Correspondence, 1916-41 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Rice: Athletics/Southwest Conference-General, 1918-27, 1938, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Rice: Athletics/Southwest Conference-General, 1953, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Rice: Civilian defense, WWII (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Rice: Design and construction of Institute buildings, 1908-27, 1940s-70s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Rice: Founder's Statue, 1930, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Rice and Houston: History and descriptions, 1938, 1967-68 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Rice: Reminiscences, history, 1930, 1938, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Architecture at Rice University:, Volumes 1-14 (Box 3)
  - Architecture at Rice University:, Volumes 15-22, 25 (Box 4)
- Series III: William Ward Watkin Personal/Family, 1920s-80s; 1 linear inch (Box 4, Folder 1-15)
  This series consists of biographical information, interviews and correspondence and related materials on his family.
  - William Ward Watkin biographical information (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - William Ward Watkin biography interviews, 1960s, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - William Ward Watkin biography correspondence, 1960s-70s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, general, 1920s-81 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Watkin family: Josephine Cockrell Watkin, Ray Watkin Hoagland, Rosemary Watkin Barrick, W.W. Watkin, Jr., 1940s-70s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - For the Future, Fitness and Harmony Pencil Points, Feb. 1932 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - William Ward Watkin bust-corresp. With McVey (sculptor), 1974-76 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Rice University Fund Council, 1973-84 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Rice University Architectural Alumni Association (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Rice University School of Architecture annual reports (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - William Ward Watkin Traveling Fellowship (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Rice Institute Traveling Scholarship in Architecture (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: William Ward Watkin to Rosemary Watkin Barrick (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Oversize materials from Box 3 (Box 5)
    - Brochure of the Work of Wm Ward Watkin, Architect, c. 1963 (Box 5)
    - The Fondren Library, The Rice Institute, Houston, TX prospectus, 1947 (Box 5)
    - Pen and ink rendering on paper by H.C. Jemison of sanctuary screen at Christ Episcopal Church, Houston [designed by W.W. Watkin], 1978 (Box 5)
    - Art Work of Houston, Texas; published in Twelve Parts; the Gravure Illustration Co., Parts 1-4, 6-12 [for complete series, see WRC F394 .H8 A88], 1904: (Box 5)
- Addenda (Box 6-11)
  - Cram, Goodhue Ferguson plans for Rice campus (copies) (Box 6(ov), Folder 1)
  - William Ward Watkin architectural sketch, University of Pennsylvania, 1908 (Box 6(ov), Folder 2)
  - Photograph, William Ward Watkin and others, Granada, Spain, 1925 (Box 6(ov), Folder 3)
  - American Institute of Architects (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Archi-Arts (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - [Rice] Architectural style (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - [Rice] Architecture Department (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - [Rice] Architecture School (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - [Rice] Athletics (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - [Committee on] Athletics (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Baldwin Memorial Archives (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - [U.S.] Board of Architectural Consultants (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Buildings, Rice campus (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - [Rice] Campus construction (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Carrington, Samuel (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Watkin-general (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Watkin/Lovett (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Cram, Goodhue Ferguson, Architects (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Cram, Goodhue Ferguson, Architects (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Cram, Ralph Adams (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Cret, Paul (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Endress Watkin (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - [Rice] Faculty (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - [Rice] Faculty Club (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Fox, Stephen (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - [The] Gables (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Guerard, Albert J. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Guion Hall (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Heitman House (Shadyside) general information (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Hooten, Claude (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Houston Chamber of Commerce (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Houston Country Club (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Houston history (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Houston Public Library reopening (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Interviews (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Interviews (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - James Stewart Company (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Keally, Francis (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Kinkaid School (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - [Rice] Landscaping (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Lassig, Oswald (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Lovett, E.O. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Martino, Tony (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - [Houston] Museum of Fine Arts (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Nicholson, Patrick J. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - No-Tsu-Oh (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Palmer Church (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Photos-Rice University (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - [Rice] President's House (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Rice history (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Rice history (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Rice master plan (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - [William Marsh] Rice statue (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Ritz Theater (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - [Rice] Seal, shield (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - [Houston] Social clubs (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - [Rice] Stadium seating plan (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Sul Ross State University (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Tellepsen, Howard T. (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Texas Tech (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - [Rice] Traveling Scholarship in Architecture (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - [Rice] Traveling Scholarship in Architecture (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Trinity Church (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Vesey, Francis (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
  - Watkin, Annie Ray Townsend (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Watkin, Nunn, McGinty Phenix Associated Architects (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Watkin, W.W.-biography and resume (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Watkin, W.W.-book, general (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Watkin, W.W.-book clean-up file (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Watkin, W.W.-book correspondence with Gulf Publishing Co. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Watkin, W.W.-book correspondence with Patrick Nicholson (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Watkin, W.W.-book layout (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Watkin, W.W.-book (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Watkin, W.W.-book layout photos (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Watkin, W.W.-bust (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Watkin, W.W.-estate, book royalties (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Watkin, W.W.-memorial fund (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Watkin, W.W.-private practice (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Watkin, W.W.-private practice, projects (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Watkin, W.W.-publications (Box 11, Folder 8-9)